welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
hello everyone and welcome to the stoah
stoah as a digital campfire where we
cohere and dialogue about what's meant
what matters most at the knife's edge my
name is Raven and I'll be the host for
the evening thank you for all for coming
for the next episode of live players
with Sam o bersia so we're gonna have
about a 20 minute talk with Sam oh and
then move into a question to answer
period that I will emcee
if you have any questions or
propositions that you want to make
during the Q&A you can go ahead and
throw those in the chat and we'll get to
them during that session and with that
Sam OH
take it away thank you very much as
always it's great to be here
looking forward to the discussion today
and I will be talking about how to find
the frontiers of knowledge
earlier today I published an essay
that's based on a previous talk I had
given on the topic I think it's very
easy to talk and it's very interesting
to talk about things such as ystem ology
making sense of the world
institutional decay transmission of
knowledge and so on this is just very
intellectually stimulating stuff but the
ultimate test of it in my opinion is is
it practical right can it be practically
applied in this essay and also like a
little bit in this talk I dropped the
links in the in the chat section I try
to apply it in a straightforward way I
think that fields have not yet been
fully defined so we have not yet
exhausted the possible intellectual
questions we can ask that are worthy of
years of study order it might have
multiple breakthroughs left in them just
as in the 1820s there was no conception
of biochemistry but the next field of
biochemistry remains to be made if
you're searching for the existing
institutions to provide you with an
introduction to this field you'll be
disappointed there's actually no
possible way to do it especially I would
argue in an academic context where you
are rewarded for making small claims not
rewarded for making large productive
exploratory hypotheses to define a new
field you
have to do large exploratory hypotheses
that completely reinterpret the old set
of data right the methodological jump
from anthropology to sociology to
economics to political science you might
be describing the exact same political
phenomena which are going to be using
different standards and relying on
different literature's for each of those
right so even if we're looking at a
small subset of a problem such as
analyzing you know say a tribal
chieftain of some kind you would be
using these very different conceptual
networks but if your conceptual network
is made completely outside of an
institutional context it's usually not
going to be recognized by intellectual
authorities there's a reason the term
crackpot carries the stigma that it does
because it suggests an anti-social
obsession with knowledge and secondarily
a possibly bad set of fact-checking I'm
going to however claimed that the word
crackpot doesn't even imply that the
person is wrong I think the strongest
connotation is that it's an outsider
that the person is an outcast that their
knowledge even if they are correct has
no bearing on the world to make an
argument that this is in fact the common
usage I know - the role of crackpots in
Hollywood movies right if we take
Hollywood movies to be a good
representation of America's subconscious
and unconscious beliefs about the world
the crackpot with the wild conspiracy
theory about the CIA and the FBI and the
State Department and the president that
person is usually right in a Hollywood
movie but there's still like this person
that you don't want to be or don't want
or help and don't want to associate with
so what's up with that and I think it's
very we love pretending that it's you
know the epistemology is so bad and that
if only the thinking is good we will put
it up in Center and the thinking the
idea is the truth the facts of the
matter we now in impartial public
discourse all the while pretending that
this is the case we also firmly believe
that you know there's like massive
gatekeeping and that the narrative is
massively controlled and that there's
you know psyops running all over the
place and that everyone's insane and
that their biases are throwing them out
that their foreign to see
information operations trying to drive
you to extremism well which one is it
right you can't legitimize the second
with the first yet we do this political
alchemy we engage in it all the time
we legitimize the insanity by recourse
to the world of the ideal so I think
that the first step then in a practical
epistemology is to decide or try to
figure out is the field you are
interested in working has it already
crystallized perhaps under a different
name right it ultimately if you're
studying a tribal chief them it doesn't
matter if you have to be an economist if
you have to be a political scientist if
you have to be a sociologist or an
anthropologist to study triangle
kingdoms you just want the actual matter
the actual subject of study you don't
want the title I assume if you're
motivated by knowledge itself so you
should then take a look where would be
easiest to study where will you be both
the best informed by an existing
tradition of knowledge that has highly
useful concepts and have the freedom to
make your own additional contributions
so it's quite possible that a field is
miss named I would say that in 1970s
America the best sociological insights
were found among people who who had the
title of economists right
recently Robin Hanson proposed that
there should be studied for generalists
right but the reality is a lot of people
are already generalists they just have
very different titles we call them
writers or we call them economists what
we call them sometimes philosophers the
philosopher one is currently gate kept
by academic recognition the writer one
is the only one that's cleanly not gate
kept by academic recognition for an
economist it's possible to get away with
not having a PhD in economics as long as
you have something useful or attached
some kind of institutional position so
it can be in the private sector and for
philosopher you just basically have to
have tenure and ten years become just
like much more difficult to achieve
there are some like other controversial
ways like
I'm not going to like trying to capture
all the edge cases I'm transferring
trying to capture 90% of the cases of
which individuals are publicly allowed
to think right and this has been a topic
I've talked about in previous episodes
in the essay I described like the key
places where you might find knowledge so
you might find it if it's already
crystallized in an existing functional
institution you actually have to look at
the institution is functional or if it's
grown dysfunctional if it's grown
dysfunctional you're actually going to
have a very negative experience trying
to advance knowledge further because the
stated mission of the organization plus
the actual discovery of new knowledge
these are just incompatible priorities
and we'll trade off against each other
harshly there's the classic saying that
science advances one funeral at a time I
think this is not true I think this is
true in a very dysfunctional version of
science and you know if it's true for
many fields then perhaps many fields are
dysfunctional right now or have hit
their limits long ago second one
communities of practice communities of
practice can be driven by either an
economic niche or social niche in
reality of course all mushas are
socio-economical there's no such thing
as a subculture that doesn't have
economic consequences or economic
processes and there's no such thing as
an economic niche without social
processes running right I would argue
that you know the relationship between a
doctor and a patient is like deeply
deeply social it's not a market exchange
I would even go further and say that you
know the relationships between people in
a white-collar office environment are
social relationships not just economic
relationships and then also you know I
think almost all voluntary societies are
providing sometimes with non-mac market
mechanisms some material benefits to
members of various kinds they can pool
risk and the bundle risk and I think
that's very important many people who
lie on these communities for what in
theory insurance should provide right
especially in the domains of like state
health care or or social safety
beyond communities of practice you can
also learn how to identify the sort of
you know unusual individuals who are
already masters of their craft or sort
of like these exceptionally talented
thinkers who are like you know the peak
of the peak skill of artistry or
sculpting or mathematics and you can
just try and actually learn from those
directly really nothing stops you you
can easily send them a cold email you
can show up at their home do their
gardening or help them out review their
papers maybe co-author with them knowing
that they get the lion's share of the
credit for any paper they co-authored
with you
meanwhile you get the lion's share of
the learning these kind of steps where
you start by evaluating institutions you
then go and evaluate the sociological
reality of the institutions and then you
choose whether to institutionalize
yourself and note if you're going into
an R&D lab you are institutionalizing
yourself just as much as if you checked
yourself into a hospital or into a
prison right we live in extremely
regimented societies sometimes that's
the right call
but it's actually a burden of evidence
to show that it's the right call either
you go this type of institutionalization
and the sociological sense you either
join the community of practice that
still has a landscape of social
incentives that point towards the
intellectual excellence and skill in a
domain or you basically try to
apprentice yourself to someone and make
it economically and socially viable for
them to invest massively into you if you
are an asset you will be invested in if
you are competitor you will not be
invested in I think this is just so
deeply deeply true and it's one of the
reasons also that the current doctoral
adviser or system is a fraud it's a
fraud because the doctoral advisors have
no personal career stake in the success
of their own students that would be
commensurate with the investment they
would have to given their students
so what persists then is only the
economically exploitive relationship as
you know again well pointed out by
others so I would love to hear questions
now not just on this
her this short part where I sort of
talked through some of these ideas of
where you can pursue excellent knowledge
and so on but also on the article I
linked and any questions I'm very
welcome
great so anybody who has a question or a
proposition can go ahead and put it into
the chat and then I will call your name
and you can ask your question directly
to Sam oh and while people are getting
their brains flowing Sam oh I just
thought could you connect this specific
talk to the overarching kind of thing
that you're doing with live players what
does this question of how to find the
frontiers of of knowledge have to do
with with life players surviving in the
contemporary society well it's not just
surviving it's thriving right why bother
to be adaptive to new circumstances I
think many life players you know some of
the greatest intellectual contributions
in history were made by people who are
live players they have to be adaptive to
their environment because if their
insight was counterfactually already
factored in by people in a particular
institution then they might as well not
have engaged in that intellectual labor
I think that it is very easy to save
years or decades of time and dead ends
by doing the thing that actually makes
sense rather than focusing on some sort
of strange performative like how do I
put this knockoff of knowledge I think a
lot of people spend a lot of their
energy in you know these kind of
ego-syntonic fantasies where they pursue
the appearance of knowledge so much more
than in substance and I think that right
now one of the key tasks at hand is have
there being enough individuals who are
live players that they can generate
entirely new frontiers of knowledge and
operationalize that knowledge in action
so I think that it's very important to
it either young or old so this applies
as much to the 40 or 50 year old
software
engineer that has figured out that it's
depressing to be a software engineer
where you've paid a lot of money to
build like moderately bad products or
the person that is 15 is trying to
figure out whether they should like
enroll in college and presumably they
both have like a lot of brain power
right wouldn't it be great to apply that
brain power to the substance of
knowledge rather than the appearance of
intelligence like at one point you
really have to let go of intelligence
signaling and just like look at the
thing itself and only if just a few
people do this I think we are vastly
enriched intellectually as a society so
I also think that recognizing people how
people might find knowledge most
effectively is a good way to diagnose
the existence of life players right so
you can study for example you know Elon
Musk's famous auto didactical approach
with rocket rocket design engineering
where he just grabbed the textbooks and
learned like isn't that so different
than trying to like work in the
aerospace industry or something or like
getting a PhD in it he could have chosen
that you know it would have been
probably less time efficient Aneesh
would you like to ask your question hi
am i audible oh yes wonderful so I just
I just read out the question because
it's pretty pretty um do you think
there's currently enough economic and
human surplus today that if there were a
single life player capable of
coordinating the incentives a competitor
to classical academia would be viable
not the classical academia but certainly
to current academia because I think
current academia is like ludicrously
human capital inefficient and it's also
inefficient in terms of capital like I
think it would be very easy to compete
with literally all of contemporary
academia in the narrow domain of
knowledge production for about two
billion dollars a year and something
like 300 very very talented thinkers
beginning would be just very easy to do
that and
you know if you didn't want to compete
but merely wanted to push on the
productive frontier it could probably be
done with 50 excellent people and
something like a hundred million dollars
a year but you know I think that the
best way to think about contemporary
academia is that they are a that you
know they are they're the cult of the
librarian recording cataloging and
cross-indexing known human knowledge
grown to vast proportions like I think
you know in the distant future there
should definitely be librarians there
should be many of them but they
shouldn't be pretending that they are
the originators of most human knowledge
they're not and this like strategic
overreach of academia into the domain of
all knowledge production just because
there was some talented academics in
1940's America who made the atomic bomb
who by the way learn how to think
outside of academia right like you know
Einstein and so on right
or learned in an academia that was
really different from current academia
like that just seems this vast
structural overstretch and then
connecting into a system of indentured
labor such as the grad school student
system that's like bizarre I think like
you know future historians will likely
be having a field day trying to explain
this to future societies so classical
academia though I think was more
intellectually productive especially if
we talk about the German research
university but that's because it was
tied into a very different
socio-economic system or was inherently
elitist and inherently self-limiting
rather than in America where the
Prussian research university was
connected to upward social mobility I
mean you know it is impossible to
promise an entire society upward social
mobility because upward social mobility
is about relative position so it's an
impossible thing to promise yes I'm
saying like one interpretation of the
American dream is inherently impossible
it's self contradictory it's self
exploding other interpretations such as
rising living standards that's fine that
can work but the interpretation of like
massive upward mobility through the
research university makes it be not a
very good research university and the
research university by the way was the
idea that under if the
academics are not competing too much
with each other so if the librarians are
not competing with each other who
produces the most index cards
cross-referencing human knowledge a
library is not a bad place to do
thinking so if you can publish once
every few years and you're fine and you
present your own findings in you
immediately catalog your own findings
that would be a pretty good way to
contribute to human knowledge but it's
been long competed away out of that and
I still think there are many brilliant
people who are contributing to human
knowledge that live in academia but I
feel it's draining their energies rather
than contributing to them I can testify
to that well I hope I hope this the the
answer was not too long and involved but
they know you did ask a big question yes
this is a slight follow-on but if
someone had significantly less money but
a more coordination ability link how
much do they fund against each other in
terms of you said 50 good people and 100
million versus you know well I think the
the money is needed to make the the
success of 50 people legible to the rest
of society I think just to support those
50 people you would probably need like 2
or 3 million a year I know a little bit
more depends on where they live they
don't have a boiler they don't have to
live in the Bay Area or New York but to
make it legible to the rest of society
you know you know if you think about the
ancient era of the Bronze Age with the
massive palace where the god king
resides with it massive pillars and
halls and gold decorations on that's
really not for the king it's kind of
like uncomfortable actually living in
Versailles your food is always cold
because it takes forever to get it from
the kitchen to where you're living
but the palace isn't for you it's for
the subjects so I think one hundred
million dollars is the amount of money I
think even with good PR strategy that is
needed for modern America society to not
to say those 50 people are actually
great researchers rather than crackpots
it's just that's just the money it takes
to do that okay thank you
that was that was usable information
Thanks
well great great i disavow crack pottery
of course like you know I endorse a
nurse reforming the whole of society
I don't endorse splintering away from it
and creating breakaway civilizations
Thank You Billy yeah have you heard of
this term super connector and and what
is the role of these super connectors in
helping like helping domains of
knowledge that aren't talking to each
other to communicate and and collaborate
and and the role of super connector is
also to have an intuition about what
things might have something that's
synergistic between some people I think
the super connectors are a mathematize
ation and subset of a much stronger term
socialite the positive social role of
socialites is to be full-time super
connectors that is people who know many
individuals and have in their recall
immediately the skill sets of those
individuals but unlike super connectors
right super connectors aren't implied
usually to be tracking people's
emotional states I actually think the
socialite tracks people's emotional
states thereby is essentially a
matchmaker for teams and I think because
the financial mechanisms are terrible
for matchmaking teams you have to rely
on social mechanisms so would actually
say that the best super connectors are
socialites in very well-developed scenes
that they have gardened
where these social incentives are
connected with the right type of
economic privilege so that the people
providing social goods are compensated
economically if you try to make it all
be market driven it just doesn't work
out somehow or it's super tricky to get
right so what you actually have to do is
I'm invoking privilege as a technical
concept and many concepts privilege is
strictly negative but I think here it's
actually positive because it allows so
economic abundance for a limited scene
of people and then if the
social incentives are correct in that
limited scene of people the socialites
can do their work full-time and it
becomes ludicrously intellectually
productive I would say the Royal Society
was originally at this basically bored
aristocrats inviting each other to check
out each other's edgings
right come see my etchings oh I mean
come see my rock collection or come see
my plant collection or come see my like
telescope isn't this a baptist curiosity
come see my library the integration of
social life intellectual contribution
and like economic abundance that you see
in the Royal Society is like sounds
fabulous if you would describe this in
concrete terms to like anyone who today
is laboring as an academic or as a
programmer as whatever it's like in
those conditions like generativity is
given right you are competing to be as
generative as you can be and I think
that those are very difficult to set up
I think some scenes in music and art
recreate this because the artists have
this alchemy where you know they find to
have an earnest relationship between the
patron with some money and taste and the
creative person with the actual energy
there is a genuine social relationship
between them it's it's not it doesn't
feel negative if it feels negative this
means the social fabric isn't there so
he feels exploited of this already means
something has gone wrong this already
means the scene is not as creative
culturally as it could be so uh sorry
instead of just answering a narrow
question about super connectors I'm
pointed to a different type of social
ideal and then I talked too much about
this social technology that's I think
behind societies research societies and
behind salons and behind the creation of
many fields like say I would argue it's
not just a royal society like the origin
of archaeology came out of the same type
of social environment where people who
are already well-off sort of competing
with each other on the creation of
knowledge and having both enough
intellectual and social savvy to not
they're not social savvy to not be
crackpots and enough intellectual savvy
to like you know be not be charlatans
cool so I hope that that answers the
question yeah
great said would you like to ask your
question yeah sure
so do you think that live players tend
to acquire knowledge through one of the
paths you mentioned rather than others
like say apprenticeship or a community
of knowledge or in the case of me one
last thing and what i Didact and just
doing a lot of reading and how would you
contrast the different approaches
between live players well I think that
it depends both on the strengths of the
person but it also depends on the state
of knowledge I think you know Auto
tactus ISM is particularly potent when
there has not been that much good work
done or when the good work that had been
done in the past is mostly abandoned so
say if you wanted to do science being an
autodidact was a great idea in 1550
because you're kind of at the dawn of
the Renaissance you can easily like do
some private experiments and read some
Aristotle and figure out wait we can we
can extend Aristotle or we can disprove
Aristotle right so you can get pretty
far that way being an autodidact would
probably been the wrong choice in 1900
if you wanted to be a contributing
physicist because there were these
amazing communities of practice like the
Olympian Society which is the one that
Albert Einstein frequented right and
then later there was a true Republic of
Letters you know I almost want to make a
joke and say latter day Republic of
Letters among physicists from 1910 to
about 1940 where you know why is
Oppenheimer citing Hindu Scripture well
because he's read Hindu Scripture he's
read a lot of it he's also read a lot of
Marx he's actually thought about a lot
of different things
and Einstein regularly would talk to the
best philosophers of his era to clarify
concepts compare the wideness of the
spirit and the intellect to the
narrowness of the modern expert right
there's something just off here there's
something wrong so I think that because
something is off and something is wrong
scenes are really hard to find today
they exist but they can be very marginal
seeming on the edge of being crackpot II
ideally you have to stay on
right edge right there is no um let's go
this way
treason doth never prosper because you
know none dare call it treason if it
does I think crackpots never prosper
because no one is called a crackpot if
they succeed right so when when you know
Isaac Newton spending half of his time
debating reading into the Bible the
correct relation of the angels and of
alchemy and the other half on gravity
we don't think think of him as a
crackpot even though in terms of a
cognitive profile he's the archetypical
crackpot like he's sticking needles in
his eyes for God's sake I mean you know
biohacking right yeah he did optics
experiments where he would stick just a
needle into his eye and you know his bet
on angels didn't work out or so or so we
think
I think but his bet on on you know
figuring out movement and gravity and
mathematize ation of those that it work
out I still I still you know if I wanted
to have a breakthrough in cognitive
science I would you know try to talk to
a cognitive scientist a young ambitious
one and say I think you should secretly
read the translations of Isaac Newton's
work on the mathematize ation of human
emotion until no one you've read them
and then try to translate them into
modern scientific language and I
guarantee you there would be at least
five or six excellent ideas that will
probably be breakthrough papers but he
must never tell anyone the secret that
he got it from Newton stuck like this
just happens all the time by the way
people are inspired by sources that are
ultimately not credited so it is
difficult to figure out what the live
players are doing sometimes right it's
difficult to figure out where they're
getting inspiration and yes the the I am
also saying that I think most
specifically theorizing about human
psychology and the interrelation of
emotions right if you go we'd say Thomas
Aquinas is theology it's very clear it's
talking about the specifications of
emotions and when they appear when they
don't appear it's not just making claims
about metaphors
it's making claims about the mind so if
people gave Newton's writing on that as
much benefit of the doubt as they gave
Buddhists writing I think it would be
interesting breakthroughs to be had but
the work of laundering Buddhism through
science it was only recently undertaken
in California so maybe one day Newton
will also be laundered through modern
science cool next question yeah Danielle
would you like to ask your question
Oh your audio seems dead uh yes okay
great yeah so when I asked the question
you have to get it specifically spoken
seems and the past I think three
questions you speaking excessively sings
so I will try to extend I'll try to
extend the question since you've covered
so much already this is basically I know
that it's there aren't a lot of very
visible live players right now there are
a lot of scenes you know they're kind of
things showing up on the crackling side
and they're sputtering out what are ways
that some are sputtering out what do you
think might be the best chance is to
like take one and get it to not sputter
out throw it from there so say assembly
you what there's natural world I don't
know we could have also talking about
making a new one but really is there a
sign of life anywhere because everyone's
asking where let me go what if leave the
cities maybe where do you go you know
the United States fleeing you know this
is a good one of Constantinople getting
taken over by the Turks and then
everyone ends up in Pisa and then you
get the Renaissance so is it less
equivalent I mean I think you're also
asking about the intellectual
productivity of cities here implicitly
where cities cities a scene as always
hosted in a city right and depending on
the era it might be Paris right the
Paris of the salons it might be ancient
Alexandria people don't know this but
briefly a British occupied Alexandria
was also an intellectual center where
random Europeans would go and hang out
um yeah and Vienna was such a city and
so on well the thing is that I think
there are several scenes that are quite
intellectually productive that have but
I think it's always useful to if you see
a failed scene or a dying scene that you
take a subset of the people and redefine
something right next to the old scene
that however only attracts this subset
because two to three reasons
signal-to-noise ratio number two the
ability to forge new Ledger's of social
accounting because if I know someone in
the context where we are both like say
Mormons and we're members of the Mormon
Church or something like this and all of
these like ways in which we track our
behavior towards each other it produces
the equivalent of like an economic
ledger like a set of depths debts and so
on so there has to be a way for the old
scene to declare a jubilee where the old
debts are forgiven so that's why
creating a completely new scene where
the old Ledger's of accounting are no
longer like considered valid this
implicit social tracking of Faber's
responsibility guilt commits - creates
exactly exactly and well again in the
first point goes okay signal-to-noise
create a new social ledger number three
is usually you have to find something
new economically I think that there's
this beautiful beautiful opportunity for
all the people who have become
personally economically free from
technology to grow as human beings and
become the next cultural frontier of
America I think the West Coast is an
amazing place in terms of economic space
for this cultural flourishing what it
lacks though is an awareness that we
have to turn away from pure abstraction
and turn towards the human - let me make
it happen thank you
I agree I've been thinking I'm trying to
establish this some sort of colony
somewhere certainly combined
intellectual and artists calling me that
safe and fire assets on
thinking inside the United States might
be outside but somewhere they get me
there needs to be a connection well
several possibilities where people have
these limits on where they want to move
or where they don't want to move I I
would think that some parts of Nevada or
some parts near Seattle might be good
spots for this because they're close
enough that people can still visit their
friends in the previous region but they
have enough natural beauty to encourage
contemplation now I actually own a romic
we think natural beauty is required for
certain kinds of okay quite great I
think on the East Coast there might be
an argument to be made for like some
parts around New York but I but it feels
kind of burned out it's possible I think
it's possible to do something around New
York I think in Europe but Berlin will
be a fad I think Berlin will grow to be
an ever bigger city over time and a lot
of the stuff will you know 20 years from
now no longer be viable that's currently
viable but right now it's you have a
good artist scene all things considered
yeah thank you great so we have a
question from Charlie and I was hoping
that you could connect Charlie's
question to a question that I was asked
to read as well which is have you
identified any live players in STEM
academia and then Charlie if you want to
ask your question oh thank you yeah I'm
interested in the idea of seniors and
how that overlaps with new knowledge and
you were talking earlier about there
being these really happening creative
scenes but that they I'm thinking that
they don't necessarily give rise to new
knowledge so where is new knowledge at
the moment where do you see it happening
and can you generalize about how the new
knowledge comes about as separate to how
a senior's comes about and some seniors
of culturally creators happening stuff
and maybe something about what the
overlap is well I think that the the
cultures must exist on the frontier of
possibility where people have either
reached the next stage of their life so
there is like a coming-of-age phenomena
where the persons which is their
cultural context completely or they must
exist in the intermingling of emerging
of previously disconnected cultures so
either one is providing a bridge into
them or providing a bridge between two
separate things that merge right right
and I think the the process of the
crystallization of knowledge where there
is a lot of knowledge to synthesize
either because of the different life
experiences of the people or because of
two separate compartments coming
together because there's a lot of this
work available enough people try their
hands at intellectual synthesis and they
see each other do that that they acquire
good taste as to who is doing actual and
intellectual synthesis and who's doing
something else there has to be an
abundance almost like a cognitive
overhang right there's this concept of
computational overhang that people have
used with the idea that you know as
computers grew faster and faster and
faster but until there was a
breakthrough theoretical breakthrough in
our understanding of intelligence there
couldn't be artificial intelligence but
the faster the computers were the
smarter the artificial intelligence
would be once you figured it out I think
there's something like this with culture
even if that by the way doesn't apply to
AI is it actually exists it's just where
I got the concept right so so there has
to be cognitive overhang in the sense
that there's this overabundance of stuff
that's been separated somehow by a wall
of experience or communication that's
being breached allowing many many people
to participate and enough of the people
in the new subculture enough of them are
participating for it to be electrical
activity in that scene that is like one
of the strongest like a resource
preconditions I still think it requires
socialite and requires group norms and
so on
and eventually they run they run out of
the insight to deposit or they run out
of socialites mm-hmm so would you
analogize that to like the economic
surplus that's put back into
productivity yes yes there's a very like
a very good analogy they're very strong
mm-hmm I wish I wish we could just write
papers and that for econ journalist or
something like there's I feel like
there's material for something like 70
70 or 80 papers just in the last 30
minutes of conversation cool Thank You
Albert yeah Sam oh I love what you're
talking about right now I have like a
mind boner just listening to you and I'm
coming basically like what you're going
on about about like the academic silos
and lack of like transdisciplinary
thinking and for example you biohacking
like like I'm heavily into like healthy
nutrition alternative health hacking and
and if you know the bilat in space the
people who are at the frontier of health
of wellness they're like they're coming
from computer science they're coming
from philosophy I'm reading a book right
now by say or g-code generate he's
talking about how this whole this whole
idea that the human body derives most of
our energy via mitochondria is complete
nonsense it actually comes from the
structure of water is actually water
actually has four phases not three it's
called structured water exclusion zone
water so that's fascinating and like my
whole family they're all in the medical
sector but they know nothing about
actual health like I'm a business and
engineering major who minored in
philosophy and I want circles around
them when I talk about actually how to
live a healthy life and and basically my
point here is what do you think are the
benefits and constraints of navigating
the current meta crisis through the
framework of games because again like
I'm heavily into bio hacking and like
when I think about it I think because
the thing about games it is acts as in
like we are playing something it's
imaginary it's a myth we do have
in history of games that we played and
how we're trusted changing rules in
order the missions but I also but me I'm
playing around with with biology as as a
framework because like I look at what
human beings are doing as by becoming a
super organism I've heard people use
biological you know like that's like a
metaphor but I actually see that
literally as what we're doing right now
and I actually see also become the super
organism as like like like like
basically what we're trying to do and my
point is I believe that biology has like
countless examples of successfully
instantiated anty anty robbers games
like serial endosymbiosis where we
actually have countless solutions okay
solve games like we actually have these
systems in place I think we just need to
tap into the innate knowledge that's
embodied within biology so I just wanted
what are your thoughts on that it's a
big body too it's it's a lot to ask for
it's certainly interesting to listen and
think about takes more to evaluate of
course like you know especially it's
like lot lots of claims like takes a
while to think them all through I think
that there is massive massive overhang
between different fields of human
knowledge and there are somewhat
artificial divisions between them that
we pretend are inherent divisions you
know my intuition is the human mind is
whole it's not fragmented it can be
fragmented but it's whole so the pursuit
of knowledge and effective thinking is
whole it's a single endeavor and the
incentives again of the librarian are to
narrow it down as much as possible to
create the most defensible minimal index
card which is perhaps good as a
preservation technique much as
mummification is good for the human body
a to preserve it but it's not compatible
with with life perhaps like excessive
fragmentation is not compatible with
intellectual life so that's that will be
my first reflection on it perhaps could
go to the next question then and I can't
I can't really speak on biology right
it's not our we have expertise
great thank you so much okay I'm gonna
ask a question on behalf of Coleman how
do you think about epistemology when it
comes to current events where there are
many stories about what's happening
well there's okay I basically think that
people need to to understand current
events have a well worked out model of
how revolutions work and how they don't
work they need to have a good model of
economic production being to have a good
model on the Genesis and functioning of
religions and they probably need to know
a thing or two about stage formation and
that just handles the politics and the
geopolitics there's like stuff happening
technologically and psychologically that
I think is beyond easily accessible
material so in other words just
technologically to keep track of what's
going on you would actually need the
tacit knowledge of like several
different branches of expertise like
even to keep track of something basic
like you know solar cells becoming
cheaper over time why are they becoming
cheaper right that already is like a
non-trivial technical question and
psychologically I think we you know we
don't have canonical theories of
psychology that we deeply rely on but in
fact everyone practices you know we
practice so clearly emotional
transformation and working with other
people we all do psychological
engineering all the time everyone's
doing psyops right if you want to frame
them that way it's somehow our
exploitative theory of psychologists are
primitive so in this way I think human
beings it's I think human psychology is
not that complicated but I think we're
kind of birds right birds that know how
to fly but don't know how to design a
plane or how to like you know even
explicate the laws of aerodynamics or
something like this so I think that if
one could have a better theoretical
understanding of psychology one could
construct intelligible interpretations
of what is happening with society
that would overcome the limitations of
our intuitions because our intuitions
they're not oriented to a hundred and
eighty million voters right or talking
from 20 million voters I forget the
exact number of voters in the US there
may you know we can deal with two
hundred people maybe but you would need
to know things about the psychology of
that number of voters or that number of
citizens to make predictions on some
things about what's happening right now
or even not predictions just
explanations and I guess I am
constrained as to correct explanations
and yes I do believe that it is not just
all narrative but there exists like a
true fact of the matter there is a
physical reality there we can't always
access it though sometimes it hits us on
the head I would argue that with COBIT
what we're seeing is over and over again
the collision of the social narrative
and the raw biology of the virus and our
system is not dealing with the raw
biology of the virus very well it's not
dealing well with physical reality it is
very used to salesmanship right and you
know America's been leveling up and
marketing in demagoguery for what 200
years now so we shouldn't be surprised
that it's gotten so so deeply a mesh in
this MMO yep oh right thank you my would
you like to ask a question uh yeah can
you hear me yes okay so I actually have
a couple of questions but I'll try to
distill it down to two through something
more essential one thing I'm sort of
were interested in knowing your thoughts
on are sort of you know if you were
allowed to sort of imagine an ideal
situation it's sort of the ideal
institution for the purpose of knowledge
creation and distribution sort of what
would those core principles be and this
is kind of stemming from the fact that
you know I don't know how familiar you
are with sort of what goes on on Wall
Street Wall Street in different kinds of
institutions where there seem to be a
lot of corporation
and banks and investment firms which are
heavily involved in the process of
trying to understand the world
understand how it works
and sort of produced knowledge their
reports coming out all the time so as a
corporation a viable entity for the
purpose of knowledge production or are
there fundamental sort of flaws there
which which would make it not good for
that kind of purpose long term so what
so that's just kind of like one thought
sort of what is the ideal sort of
knowledge producing institution what are
the core principles on which its it's
built see I'll leave it at that and I'd
like to hear thoughts on that I think
corporate the corporate structure can be
compatible with knowledge production the
classic example would just be Rand the
RAND Corporation though arguably that's
bootstrapping off of the National
Defense state as was built in 1940's
right military-industrial complex but
yeah the RAND Corporation produced
decent research I think Microsoft is a
corporate body produces good research in
Microsoft's you know little corner the
labs arguably did the same thing so it
can be a good spot to do research it's
not necessarily the most natural space
but it solves the problem of creating
socio-economic Nisha's right so you know
and it eat at times produces these
islands of economic abundance so I don't
think the profit motive is actually that
helpful in generating knowledge it can
be very helpful in generating for
encouraging practical implementation of
knowledge so I think that perhaps
there's this very subtle distinction
much as exist between like you know
between production of knowledge and
conservation of knowledge there might
exist a subtle distinction between the
application the production of knowledge
now I think that I think if someone is
claiming to merely produce knowledge
with having no thought as to what
they'll be used for I think they are
lying
or rather they are confused about their
own motivations because I think almost
all knowledge production priorities have
embedded in them right just as Mike you
might have something embedded in a
market I think everyone has embedded
intent and you know what is most
interesting to them what is joyful what
is restorative and that this means that
there is like kind of a teleology of
knowledge right cool
so I hope that then at least answers the
question somewhat well I mean I I kind
of I wanted to asked it because I
figured it would be perhaps somewhat
controversial but I was I was I was
curious to know even in a if you were to
sort of step back from any one
particular kind of institution or
corporation or a university just sort of
put those models that exist to the side
and just kind of think you know sort of
ideally what what are the fundamental
principles of an institution which is
sort of sense of knowledge production
and distribution yeah I mean you have to
have a situation that one socio-economic
position is not endangered by producing
by producing excessive knowledge yet it
is not built up by producing fake
knowledge so in other words the
disinformation as an incentive has to be
very low right in both ways both in
faking production faking knowledge
faking stuff even when you don't have it
and in the direction of not being
punished for producing the wrong the
wrong object now again here I will say
there is something subtly problematic
with the perspective of academic freedom
and even freedom of speech they don't
think we have a good social
technological solution to I lean in that
direction because I don't have a better
solution but there is a subtle problem
if you take my argument about the
implicit embedded intent and knowledge
production being true then it is valid
to consider certain kinds of knowledge
production evidence of bad faith action
so my view right now is like we actually
are desperate for knowledge production
so even knowledge produced in bad faith
should be rewarded and should be used
but some of it definitely has produced
uh you know for anti-social reasons
right and I think this is the real
intuitive you know like sometimes the
jock and the nerd right the nerd
sometimes has a point though he's not
gonna put it into words like you know
oftentimes the nerd is disdainful of the
jock and does look down on them and is
in fact mean-spirited towards the jock
they merely don't have the power to like
exercise it over them so I think that
sometimes the crackpot is actually ill
intention towards society and that's
like the small part of this persecution
complex that is real right so I started
by sort of mocking society's resilient
societies like firm policing social
policing between the barrier of a
professional thinker and crackpot
because the reality is people if they
follow thought will end up on both sides
of the barrier but there is a reason and
there is an interim solution that
society is adopted right so I can't
really just invent a better social
technology on the spot I think that
would be there are too many things to
factor like there's um it's it's
honestly the life of a the work of a
lifetime in great founder Theory the
creation of these new very excellent
social technologies that solve problems
of this type is the mechanisms to which
history is driven forward right more so
than material production because I feel
material production exists and necessary
symbiosis with that so I think that this
is uh it's it's the work of a lifetime
it's the work of genius
it's from now at least I would I would
say that you know I think it is beyond
beyond my like intellectual authority to
speak on that
thank you right okay so we're kind of
closing in here maybe for our last
question here she would you like to ask
your question sure yeah
so you were talking about like how if
you had like a hundred million dollars
and fifty people that's like kind of the
unit of functioning the seemed ideal to
you and I was wondering if you had that
like access to those resources what
would you be doing with it
well I didn't say I would have it I said
hypothetical you or like a group right
so if there was I'm just curious what
you would utilize those resources well
there would be several things that would
be there would be grad school
credentials but with actual intellectual
excellence you would create a community
of intellectual excellence that at the
end would give people bureaucratically
legible credentials and there would be
also a PR publication machine where they
would be connected to book deals this
would give them both public legitimacy
and bureaucratically legible legitimacy
and the currently tenured would have to
argue that the phd's that they have are
not real PhDs but they would just
embarrass themselves over and over again
because the papers and the books and the
visible output would just be so much
better
but eventually they would stop fighting
it and they would instead try to recruit
them to become tenured professors at
Harvard or whatever probably this would
be a 10 20 year undertaking but it's
quite doable for that amount of money
and part of part of it is of course that
you need about 20 million to I think a
bribe a second tier College with the
promise that if they allow to run this
grad school they will become a first
tier college by the time this whole
thing is over so that would require a
decently ambitious second tier
university to you know and and I'm
factoring in even if it's decently in
victress you still have to bribe them
with at least 20 million great all right
so why do you have any final words for
us
well my works be like I just I would
absolutely love it if people if they are
in the pursuit of knowledge if you are a
hobbyist you know consider that perhaps
you're just way more serious than the
professionals are because you're just
actually aiming at the thing itself and
if you believe that you as a hobbyist
are way more serious than the
professionals are well congratulations
then you should read my article again
and you should think about it so if I'm
serious and if I'm gonna win how do I
beat them right like how do I make sure
that you know this is in fact going to
be taken in by the librarians that the
librarians will say this is a valid
input we accept it and that the public
as a whole can benefit from your
knowledge production because I think
there's this massive massive need for
clearly communicated knowledge that is
not playing intelligent signaling games
do you guys know how like the stock
market is utterly disconnected from the
physical economy right now well I think
the intellectual Authority market is
like radically disconnected from actual
intellectual productivity right now I
think it's been really inflated for a
long time I think we've done the
equivalent of intellectual quantitive
easing since at least the spotnik moment
right in the aftermath of Sputnik it
became important for the u.s. to
mass-produce engineers so it could
produce as many engineers as the Soviet
Union seemed to have been producing of
course the reality is while the Soviet
Union had many excellent engineers they
were lying about the number of
high-quality engineers they were
producing just as they were lying about
the number of shoes they were producing
and when the Soviet Union collapsed that
Bluff was called the US has not yet
collapse of the USS blog post Sputnik
there has all of these great scientists
has not been called yet it will be one
data it will be so take your knowledge
seriously you are responsible for it and
you're responsible for bringing it to
everyone's benefit thank you thank you
so much all right I'm going to do a
little PSA of what events we have coming
up tomorrow so we have as usual the
psycho technology playground was going
to
in the morning at 10 a.m. we also have a
upcoming session focusing felt senses as
as the liminal with Abby wen Wu and Zack
Valentini that'll be at 3:00 p.m. I will
be doing Socratic speed-dating at 7:00
and then we will also have the dark
stoah with Pat Ryan at 8:30 check us out
at the stoy dot CA if you would like to
see our other upcoming sessions and I
also want to say a big thank you for
everyone who's been giving gifts to us
at the stoah deeply appreciate it we see
the gusto as a gift in this time of need
and if you feel inspired to give a gift
yourself you can visit the styloid on CA
/ gift and thank you so much for being
here today Sam oh ok bye everybody
a pleasure